Guide to the J. Leslie Dunstan Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
J. Leslie Dunstan papers
1936-1969
RG 284
Yale University Divinity School Library
4.75
(10 boxes)
The Dunstan Papers document his professional life, primarily as a faculty member at Andover Newton Theological School. The correspondence (1936-1954) is that of Dunstan and Paul S. Minear, and provides detailed accounts of the life and work of both men during that period. Minear was a professor of Biblical Theology at Yale Divinity School.
Dunstan, J. Leslie (John Leslie), 1901-
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1901 November 21 Born in London, England
1923 Graduated from Colby College, Maine
1923-1925 Graduate work at Boston University, School of Religious Education
1928-1933 Graduate work at Union Theological Seminary, NY Ordained in Presbyterian Church, 1932 April 25 Director of Religious Education, Union Church, Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, NY
1933-1938 Associate Pastor, Central Union Church, Honolulu, Hawaii Lecturer in·Psychology and and. Philosophy of Religion, School of Religion, University of Hawaii
1935-1936 Graduate work at Westminster College, Cambridge, England
1938 Received Ph.D., Columbia University
1938-1954 Director, School of Religion, University of Hawaii
1944-1954 General Secretary of Hawaiian Evangelical Association
1954-1956 Associate Professor of Missions and Comparative Religion, Andover Theological Seminary
1956-1961 Professor of Missions and Comparative Religion, Andover
1961-1962 Montgomery Professor of Missions and Comparative Religion, Andover
1962-1969 Judson Professor of Missions and Comparative Religion, Andover Newton Theological School
1969 July 20 Died, Newton Centre, Massachusetts
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School Collection, 2017. A portion of the collection was donated to Andover Newton by Paul S. Minear in 1983.
Scope and Contents
The John Leslie Dunstan Papers, 1936-1969, document the professional work of Dunstan. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: journal, correspondence, sermons, lectures and essays, unpublished manuscripts, office files.
The correspondence (1936-1954) is that of Dunstan and Paul S. Minear, and provides detailed accounts of the life and work of both men. The sermons comprise the bulk of the collection, and are arranged as follows: undated, no Biblical text--alphabetically by title; undated--by Biblical text; dated items. The lectures and essays are arranged as follows: undated--alphabetically by title; dated items. There is a small number of items identified as unpublished manuscripts; refer to ANTS faculty-publications register for a record of Dunstan publications.
The office files are not part of the Minear gift. The files were transferred to the Andover Newton Theological School Library after Dunstan's sudden death in 1969. The material represents his current working files at that time, and documents his academic and professional responsibilities in the 1960s.
Arrangement
Series I. Journal, 1960-1961
Series II. Correspondence, 1936-1954
Series III. Sermons, 1937-1966
Series IV. Lectures and Essays, 1944-1967
Series V. Unpublished Manuscripts
Series VI. Office Files, 1957-1969
Dunstan, J. Leslie (John Leslie), 1901-; Andover Newton Theological School
- Journal, Series I
  - Account of sabbatical experience, 1960 September 10 - 1961 July (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence (1936-1954), is that of Dunstan and Paul S. Minear, and provides detailed accounts of the life and work of both men. See the first folder in this collection for a detailed listing of letters.
  - Dunstan to/from Paul and Gladys Minear (fragments and undated), No date (Box 1)
  - Dunstan to the Minears, from England, Maine, and Honolulu, Hawaii, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Dunstan to Paul Minear, from Honolulu, Hawaii, 1937–1941 (Box 1)
  - Dunstan to/from Minear, primarily from Honolulu and Newton Centre, 1942–1953 (Box 1)
    Includes a few manuscript enclosures
- Sermons, Series III
  See listing in first folder this collection for complete list of sermon titles and texts.
  - Undated sermons with no text arranged by title
    - 57 sermons, from "The boy who built an altar" to "The Lord's supper", No date (Box 1)
    - 48 sermons, from "A man set under authority" to "Your faith abroad", No date (Box 2)
  - Sermons arranged by text
    - Undated sermons: Genesis - Luke, No date (Box 2)
    - Undated sermons: Luke - Acts, No date (Box 3)
    - Undated sermons: Acts - Galatians, No date (Box 4)
    - Undated sermons: Ephesians - Revelation, No date (Box 5)
    - Dated sermons, 1937–1951 (Box 5)
    - Dated sermons, 1952–1966 (Box 6)
- Lectures and Essays, Series IV
  See the first folder of this collection for a complete list of titles.
  - Undated lectures and essays arranged by title
    - "Andover and the Missions" through "Conversion", No date (Box 6)
    - "The devil" through "The youth of Hawaii looks to the past", No date (Box 7)
  - Dated lectures and essays
    - From "Y.M.C.A. annual meeting" to "Christian education", 1944–1966 (Box 7)
- Unpublished Manuscripts, Series V
  - Untitled (5 parts), No date (Box 8)
  - Bible Study - drafts, introduction, fragments, No date (Box 8)
  - Promptings (7 versions), No date (Box 8)
  - St. Paul, No date (Box 8)
- Office Files, Series VI
  - American Baptist Churches USA
    - Commission on the Ministry - Continuing Education Committee, minutes and proposals, 1967–1968 (Box 9)
  - Andover Newton Theological School
    - Church and Ministry Department: primarily proposals, some related to field education, 1967–1968 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Black Seminary Education: correspondence and proposals, 1968–1969 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Curriculum and Academic Affairs: correspondence and interoffice memos, 1965–1969 (Box 9)
    - International Students Program: proposals, 1968–1969 (Box 9)
    - Self-study Committee: proposals, 1967, no date (Box 9)
    - Seminar in Ecumenical Theology: documentation of course content, 1965–1966 (Box 9)
      Course offered 1965/66 (first semester) by ANTS, Boston University School of Theology, Episcopal Divinity School, and Harvard Divinity School
    - Seminar in Ecumenical Theology: documentation of course content, 1968–1969 (Box 10)
      Course offered 1968/69 (first semester) by BTI schools
    - Students Concerned About Andover Newton (SCAAN): student statements and faculty responses, 1969 (Box 10)
    - Syllabi, 1961–1966 (Box 10)
      CH207, CWR301, CWR304 (1965-66/2nd semester), CWR311, CWR323 (1961-62/1st semester), RE314 (1965-66/2nd semester), RE348 (1963-64/1st semester)
  - Boston Theological Institute
    - CABAL: Program Committee; primarily minutes, 1966–1968 (Box 10)
    - Continuing Education Task Force/Committee: some proposals and reports; primarily minutes, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Massachusetts Council of Churches
    - Committee on Christian Unity: minutes, 1967–1968 (Box 10)
    - Massachusetts Commission on Christian Unity: proposals, minutes, 1967–1969 (Box 10)
  - New England Ecumenical Study Conference
    - Minutes, 1966–1968 (Box 10)
  - Professors of Missions
    - Fellowship of Professors of Missions and Eastern Fellowship of Professors of Missions: minutes and correspondence, 1957–1966 (Box 10)
  - UCC/Massachusetts Conference
    - Committee on Christian Unity: minutes, 1965–1968 (Box 10)